Hudson Family Papers, 1825-1865
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Hudson Family Papers
1825-1865
Hudson family
MS 79
1 box (.5 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Papers relate primarily to physician, abolitionist, and social reformer Erasmus Darwin Hudson. Included are the manuscript and typescript of his journal, "Anti-Slavery Campaign" (1842-43); and his correspondence (1825-65) to and from family and friends includes commentary on anti-slavery and Civil War era events and personalities such as Abigail Kelley Foster, Parker Pillsbury, Wendell Phillips, and Theodore Parker.
Biographical Note
Erasmus Darwin Hudson, Sr. was born December 15,1806 in Torringford (now part of Torrington), Connecticut, to Daniel and Rhoda Fowler Hudson. He studied medicine with Dr. Remus M. Fowler in New Marlboro, Massachusetts, and continued his studies at Berkshire Medical College (Pittsfield, Massachusetts), a branch of Williams College, where he received his M.D. in 1827. That same year Hudson married Martha Turner, daughter of Deacon Isaac and Martha Humphrey Turner of Marlboro, MA. They had two sons, Erasmus Darwin, Jr. (1843-87) and Daniel Wyatt.
He had a private medical practice in Bloomfield, CT in 1828 to 1833 and worked as a physician and surgeon at the Connecticut State Emigrant Hospital. During that time, he became involved in temperance advocacy, philanthropic work and the Connecticut Anti-Slavery Society, later as the Society's lecturing agent (1838-39) and as the National Anti-Slavery Society's general agent (1839-50).. In 1850 Hudson became a general and orthopedic surgeon in Springfield, Massachusetts, then in New York City through 1880.
During the Civil War Hudson served on the Commission from the Surgeon General of the United States Army for the treatment of wounded soldiers in need of amputation and resection at a number of military hospitals. During this time he invented an orthopedic apparatus for which he received awards. Erasmus Darwin Hudson died of pneumonia on December 31, 1880 in Riverside, Greenwich, Connecticut.
[source: Inventory to Hudson Family Papers, compiled by Laurie B. Gaus, UMASS-Amherst Archives and Manuscripts October 1983]
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Hudson Family Papers relate primarily to physician, abolitionist, and social reformer Erasmus Darwin Hudson, Sr. His correspondence (1825-65) to and from family and friends includes commentary on anti-slavery and Civil War era events and personalities. Notable correspondents or individuals mentioned include abolitionist and women's rights advocate Abigail Kelley Foster, social reformers Parker Pillsbury and Wendell Phillips, and clergyman Theodore Parker. Other items of interest are E.D. Hudson Sr.'s address "Intemperance" (1828), a manuscript and typescript of his journal, "Anti-Slavery Campaign" (1842-43), and E.D. Hudson, Jr's 1864 address, "Conquest Through Self Conquest."
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.
The Hudson Family Papers were given to the Sophia Smith Collection by an unknown donor circa 1963. Additional papers of the Hudson Family are housed at the Department of Special Collections and Archives, University of Massachusetts at Amherst.
Search Terms
Abolitionists--United States--Biography--Sources; Anti-slavery movements--United States--History--Sources; Pillsbury, Parker, 1809-1898; Foster, Abigail Kelley, 1810-1887; Hudson, Erasmus Darwin, 1806-1880; Phillips, Wendell, 1811-1884; Parker, Theodore, 1810-1860; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Personal narratives; American Anti Slavery Society; Hudson family; Northampton Association of Education and Industry; Social reformers--United States--Biography--Sources; Family--United States--History--19th century--Sources; Hudson, Erasmus Darwin, 1806-1880
Additional Information
Related Material
Additional Hudson family papers are in the Department of Special Collections and Archives, University of Massachusetts Amherst.
- SERIES I. CORRESPONDENCE
  - Contents (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Hudson, Daniel Wyatt
    - Photograph n.d. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - To parents and brother 1851, 1852, 1854 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Hudson, Erasmus Darwin, Jr. to parents n.d. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Hudson, Erasmus Darwin, Sr.
    - To Erasmus Darwin, Jr. (son) 1859-64 (Box 1, Folder 5-6)
    - To Martha Turner Hudson (wife) 1855-59 (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
  - Hudson, Fowler to parents 1851-58 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Hudson, Martha to E.D. Hudson 1855, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous Hudson family correspondence 1843, 1869, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence to E.D. Hudson, Sr.
    - Bawditch, William 1855 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Church, Jefferson 1855, 1858-64 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Fowler, R.M 1856, 1869, 1870 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Parker, Theodore n.d. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Phillips, Wendell n.d. (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Seymore, Flora n.d (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Wright, Henry C. 1853, 1855 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Kossuth, Lajos to Benjamin Palmer 1852 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- SERIES II. WRITINGS
  - Hudson, E.D., Sr.
    - Temperance address and notes 1867 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Journal: partial transcript (two copies) 1842-43 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Original manuscript of journal, "Anti-Slavery Campaign" 1842-43 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Transcripts of letters to and about E.D. Hudson 1825-41, 1848 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Hudson, E.D., Jr.: commencement essay manuscript July 1864 (Box 1, Folder 24)